Your Highness,
殿下
the peach blossom pastry and preserved fruits
謝夫人のためにご注文された蜜花桃酥と
you ordered for Lady Xie have arrived.
数種の蜜漬け菓子をお持ちしました
Please have a taste
どうぞご試食ください
and see which one
どれが一番
agrees with Lady Xie best.
謝夫人のお口に合うかお確かめを
Who made this?
これは誰が作った
Lift up your head.
顔を上げよ
It's you?
お前か
Your Highness still remembers me.
殿下はわたくしめのことを覚えておいででしたか
Take the others away.
他の者たちを下がらせよ
Everyone, leave the room.
皆 下がりなさい
How do you know how to make hawthorn cake?
なぜサンザシの菓子を作れる
Before entering the palace,
わたくしめは宮仕えの前
I had a long stay at Prince Jing'an's Mansion.
靖安王府にしばらくおりました
I often heard the servants talk about
屋敷の下働きが話しているのを聞き
Lady Xie making hawthorn cake for Your Highness.
謝夫人が殿下のためにサンザシの菓子をお作りになると
So I tried my hand at making some using her method.
その作り方を真似てみたのです
Did anyone allow you to do that?
誰の許しを得て作った
Now, I get mad at the sight of hawthorn cake,
余は今サンザシの菓子を見ると
for it always reminds me
愛しい夭夭が誰かと
of who my beloved Yaoyao is with.
一緒にいるかと思い腹が立つ
Get out!
去れ
Yes.
はっ
Mother, it hurts.
母上 痛い
Do be gentle, Mother.
もっと優しく 母上
Drop the act.
まだ芝居を
It does hurt a little.
でも少しは痛いですよ
You used to dream of traveling far and wide
以前は山河を巡り
and exploring the world.
天下を旅したいと言っていたわね
After what just happened,
このような目に遭って
do you still want to do that?
まだ行きたいと思いますか
Mother,
母上
only when I left Jiankang
夭夭は剣慷を出て
did I realize what the real world is like.
初めて真の天下というものを知りました
There aren't fine clothes and lavish feasts,
贅沢な暮らしもなく
nor thousands of dazzling lights.
きらびやかな灯りもありません
Take the girl in court today as an example.
今日の広間にいたあの娘のように
Just like that, she saw her own brother
自分の兄上が目の前で
die a tragic death right before her.
惨殺されるのをただ見ていたのです
Perhaps she already
あの娘はもう生涯
lost her only family.
身寄りがいないのかもしれません
To add to that...
それに
nobody will ever fix a honey drink for her anymore.
もう誰も甘いお湯を作ってくれません
By contrast, some people are utterly vile,
でも 人の心はあんなにも邪悪になれるのですね
just like Cui Jun.
あの崔浚のように
He even harmed his own little sister
雀骨令のために
just for the Phoenix Heart Tokens.
実の妹さえ手にかけるのですから
Right.
そうね
Empress Wenxi and I were as close as sisters.
私は文熹皇后と姉妹のように親しく
She often talked about her older brother
よくお兄様の話を聞きました
to me, describing him as an upstanding
皇后のお兄様は 大義を胸に抱く
and ambitious man.
志の高いお方だと
To survey the mineral deposits of Ye,
大鄴の鉱床を調査するために
he travelled to nearly every part of the country.
国中を歩き回ったとか
But based on what Cui Jun did today,
ですが今日の崔浚の行いは
he is completely different from what Empress Wenxi said.
文熹皇后が話していた人物とはまるで別人でした
I've never seen this.
会ったことはありません
Then, has there been
では そなたの父上は
anything odd about your father after he returned
漠北の旅から戻られた後
from the northern desert region?
何か変わったことはありましたか
I once heard from my mother
母から聞いたことがあります
that my father was severely injured
父は漠北から戻った時
upon his return.
ひどい傷を負っていたと
After he recovered,
傷が癒えた後は
he became completely different.
まるで別人のようでした
He was cold, indifferent,
冷淡で
violent, and harsh,
厳しくなり
unlike the loving parent he used to be.
昔の優しさは消えてしまいました
Shortly after that, my mother passed away.
それから間もなく母は亡くなりました
Please think again.
もう一度よく思い出してみて
Any other change?
他には
My mother also told me
母はこうも言っていました
that my father somehow
理由は分かりませんが
became interested in studying
父は鉱床と地図の
mineral deposits and maps.
研究を好むようになったと
Please think again.
もっと考えてみて
What does your father
父上は普段
enjoy eating?
好きな食べ物は
He doesn't like or dislike
特に好きな物も
anything in particular.
嫌いな物もありません
However, in recent years,
ただ ここ数年
I've noticed that my father no longer enjoys tea.
父はお茶をあまり飲まなくなり
Instead, he prefers milk
逆に牛乳や
and all sorts of pastries made with milk.
牛乳を使った菓子を好むようになりました
This wheel?
ルーレット
Why does he have this?
なぜ こいつがこれを
Isn't it what I made for Shao Yang
これは昔 北秦で
years ago in Northern Qin?
少秧さんに作ったものではないか
You disappeared for 20 years.
20年も姿を消していたとは
I really thought
てっきり
you were dead,
死んだものかと
Chu Zhu.
楚竹
Nothing gets past you.
やはり あなたの目はごまかせませんか
You put on a disguise mask
顔を変え
and began hiding in Southern Ye.
南鄴に潜んでいたのは
Shao Yang instructed you to do so, right?
少秧さんの差し金だろう
This is my master's order
ご主人様の命令であり
and my mission.
私の使命です
Then what about the real Cui Jun?
では 本物の崔浚は
Twenty years ago, when he travelled the northern desert region,
20年前 彼が漠北を旅していた時
I killed him in an attempt to seize the map of mineral deposits
描いた鉱床の地図を奪うため
drawn by him.
殺しました
Unfortunately, I was one step too late.
残念ながら一足遅く
He had already sent the map back to the Capital.
地図はすでに上京へ送られた後でした
This map was later
その地図は
stashed in the Phoenix Heart Tokens
のちに文熹皇后によって
by Empress Wenxi.
雀骨令の中に隠されました
Let me ask you. Did you also orchestrate
聞くが 安陸の二氏と
the wrongful cases involving the An and Lu families
我が一族の冤罪も
and causing my clansmen's deaths?
お前の仕業か
I am a slave bought by Shao Yang.
私は少秧様に買われた奴隷
She is my master.
あの方は私のご主人様です
Whatever she asks me to do,
あの方の命令とあらば
I will absolutely do it
生きている限り
as long as I'm still breathing,
必ずやり遂げます
including eliminating the An and Lu families and your clansmen,
安陸の二氏と
as she commanded.
あなたの一族の抹殺もです
Well, well.
そうか
Not only did my love betrayed me,
恋人だけでなく
but my best friend also stabbed me in the back.
親友にまで裏切られるとはな
Not long ago in Jiankang,
先日 剣慷で
I met Shao Yang.
少秧さんに会った
How is my master doing?
ご主人様はご無事でしたか
Your master
お前の主人は
got seriously ill.
重病を患い
She passed away shortly after returning to Northern Qin.
北秦に戻って間もなく亡くなった
Will you continue to work for her?
まだあの女のために命を懸けるのか
This is a design of mine
これは私が設計した
for sealing the imperial mausoleum
皇陵を造るためのものだ
with water.
注水で封をする
Tell me.
言え
What exactly are you trying to do?
いったい何をする気だ
To destroy Lingfeng Fort.
凌風堡を破壊する
All the iron-contaminated water in the mine
鉱洞の汚染された溶鉄は
is sealed under this wheel.
すべてこのルーレットの下に封じられている
Six hours ago,
6時間前に
I already activated the wheel.
ルーレットは起動させた
Lingfeng Fort will soon be submerged by the polluted water.
間もなく溶鉄が凌風堡をのみ込み
Everyone will die.
全員死ぬ
You're crazy.
狂ってやがる
The wheel mechanism is full of hidden weapons.
ルーレットの仕掛けには暗器が張り巡らされている
Mulian Ying,
穆連嬰さん
you will definitely not
行けば
make it back alive.
必ず死にます
All of you will have to die with me!
お前ら全員 道連れだ
My mother just made some honey water.
母上が作った蜜湯です
I brought a bowl of it for you.
あなたの分も持ってきたので
Drink it when it's warm.
温かいうちにどうぞ
You didn't poison it, did you?
毒でも入れたか
Yes, I did.
入れたわよ
I added in stuff like datura,
マントラに
aconite, and Qianji poison.
トリカブトに 牽機薬よ
Why did you still drink it when I told you it was poisoned?
毒を入れたって言ったのに 飲むのね
Because I wanted to be killed by you.
お前に毒殺されたくてな
Is it sweet?
甘い
Thank you for saving those girls.
あの子たちを助けてくれて ありがとう
If they decide to hush them for good,
口封じに殺せば
what will happen to these girls?
この娘たちはどうなる
-Please help us!
どうか お助けを
-Help us!
助けて 助けてください
-I beg you! -Please!
お願いします
-Please help us!
どうか私たちを助けてください
Also, thank you for saving my mother.
母上を助けてくれて感謝する
Does your wound still hurt?
体の傷はまだ痛むか
It's normal to get injured in battle.
戦でのケガなど日常茶飯事だ
This wound is barely anything.
これくらい何でもない
My hunch tells me something's wrong.
どうも腑に落ちない
Is it about Cui Jun?
ですが 崔浚のことで
When my mother was in Shangjing years ago,
母が昔 上京にいた頃
she heard from Empress Wenxi
文熹皇后から聞いた話では
that the latter's brother was originally a righteous man.
兄君は元々 大義あるお方だったのに
But now this man has become completely different.
今では見る影もなくなったと
You don't think
彼があっさり捕まるとは
he'll easily surrender, right?
思えないのではありませんか
My own design can't stump me, can it?
俺の設計が 俺の足止めになるか
Shao Yang, here I come.
少秧 来たぞ
Your Highness, the mine collapsed.
世子様 鉱洞が崩落し
Yuan Xiaoliu is dead.
元小六が死にました
Xiao Wuyi!
蕭無衣
Yuan Xiaoliu.
元小六
Master.
師匠
Wake up.
しっかりしろ
Yuan Xiaoliu.
元小六
Master!
師匠
How exactly did this happen?
一体どういうことだ
It was my father's doing.
父が
He tried to drag everyone to hell with him.
我らもろとも道連れにする気だ
All the polluted groundwater
汚染された地下水が
was kept beneath this mine.
すべてこの鉱山の下に封じられている
My father activated the mechanism
父が仕掛けを作動させ
so as to drown the entire Lingfeng Fort with filthy water
汚水で凌風堡を水浸しにするつもりだ
and take everyone's life.
我々は皆 死ぬ
Xiao Wuyi!
蕭無衣
You cannot kill him.
殺してはだめ
We must bring him back to Jiankang.
彼を剣慷へ連れ帰らねば
That's the only way to expose the Cui family's crimes to the world
そうしてこそ崔氏の罪を世に知らしめ
and truly avenge those who died a wrongful death!
無念の死を遂げた者たちの仇を討てるのです
This is how justice works!
それが天の道です
Your master sacrificed his life to save all of ours.
お前の師匠は命懸けで我々を救った
Princess Yunzhao,
郡主様
truth to be told,
実を申しますと
I'm here at the Grand Tutor's request.
私も太傅様より頼まれて参りました
He knew you were likely in Lingfeng Fort,
太傅様は郡主様が凌風堡におられるやもしれぬと
so he asked me to bring you a message.
私に伝言を託されたのです
That is, The Xie family in Jiankang
剣慷の謝氏は
will always await your safe return.
永遠に郡主様の無事の帰りを待つと
No need. All ties between him and me are severed
お構いなく 離縁したからには
now that we are divorced.
未練はありません
You are such a free spirit.
郡主様は見事なお方
How admirable.
この楽君 感服いたしました
After the disastrous happening,
この災いを経て
I finally realized
この楽君も知りました
that the Phoenix Heart Tokens
この世にまさか
truly exist in the world.
雀骨令が存在するとは
There has always been a saying among people in recent years—
近年 巷では噂が流れています
"When the Phoenix Heart Tokens appear, peace shall be restored in the world."
“雀骨現れ 天下定まる”と
I wonder if you...
郡主様
If the world could be changed
もし数枚の令牌で
by just a few tokens,
世を変えられるのなら
why would Young Lord Xiao bother to implement reforms?
蕭世子は何のために改革を
The Phoenix Heart Tokens
この雀骨令は
are simply something that Empress Wenxi
文熹皇后が近しい者に
left behind for those around her to remember her by.
贈った形見にすぎません
As for that rumored Crown Prince Wenxi,
文熹太子なるものも
it's pure nonsense.
全くのでたらめです
That day in court,
あの日 堂上で言ったのは
I made a lie out of it
崔浚を追い詰め 自滅させるための
just to cause Cui Jun to panic.
噓だったのです
As a holder of a Phoenix Heart Token,
そなたも雀骨令を持つ者
you were also entrusted with Ye's moving to the south
大鄴の南渡を担い
and the task of aiding Crown Prince Wenxi.
文熹太子を補佐する役目です
Crown Prince Wenxi died a long time ago.
文熹太子はとうに亡くなりました
He didn't die!
あの方は亡くなっておりません
Empress Wenxi and I were as close as sisters.
私は文熹皇后と姉妹同然の間柄
If her son had really survived,
もしあの方のお子が本当に生きておられるなら
I would love him dearly.
どれほどかわいがったことでしょう
How would I have never shown any care
どうして長年
for him during these years?
気にもかけずにいられましょうか
Good then.
それならよかったわ
I was just worried about my brother.
さきほどまで兄上のことを案じておりました
If Crown Prince Wenxi truly existed,
もし本当に文熹太子がおられたら
what would become of my brother?
兄上はどうなってしまうのかと
Hearing what you said today,
本日 郡主様のお話を聞いて
I'm finally relieved.
ようやく安心いたしました
I shall
では この楽君
take my leave then.
これにて失礼いたします
How did it go? Did you intercept the letter?
どうだ 傍受できたか
Did Princess Yunzhao mention the whereabouts of Crown Prince Wenxi?
郡主は文熹太子の行方に言及したか
Bring the nanny in Prince Qi's Mansion back to Jiankang.
岐王府の乳母を剣慷へ連れ帰れ
Your brother
そなたの兄上は
is not of royal blood at all.
大鄴の血筋ではないのだ
Yunzhao has long suspected Prince Qi's origin.
雲昭はとうに岐王の出自を疑っていた
The purpose of her trip to Guazhou
今回の鴰州行きは
is probably to use the Phoenix Heart Token she holds
恐らく手持ちの雀骨令を使い
to command the other token holders
他の所持者たちに号令をかけ
to assist the Li lineage of the royal house in gaining the throne.
新たに李鄴の宗室を立てるためだろう
This is bad. She plans to reveal Mao's real identity.
まずい 兄上の正体を暴く気だ
This is the map of Ye.
これは我が大鄴の地図よ
Close your eyes.
目を閉じて
Throw a dart.
矢を投げて
We will go wherever it lands.
刺さった所へ行きましょう
No need to shut my eyes.
目隠しはいらないわ
I'll just throw the dart.
そのまま投げる
There's a place called the Cloud Pavilion on Lai Lake.
莱湖に水上雲間という場所があるの
Let's go to Lake Lai then.
じゃあ 莱湖に行きましょう
You don't like it?
嫌い
How about we will travel all the way south
では 南へ下って
in quest of the best copper mine in the world?
最高の銅鉱を探しに行きましょう
Mother,
母上
actually, I...
あの
Never mind. It's nothing.
いえ 何でもありません
So you don't like traveling with me.
母と旅をするのは嫌なの
Where would you like to go then, Yaoyao?
では夭夭 どこへ行きたいの
Oh, right.
そうだわ
I just recalled another wonderful place,
いい場所を思いついたわ
where you can find your favorite dish, tofu steamed in lotus leaves.
あなたの好きなハスの葉豆腐があるわ
In midsummer, you can take a boat out to sea.
夏には船で海に出られるし
How about we venture off to the sea
母が海に連れていってあげる
and watch the sunrise together?
海から昇る朝日を見るのはどう
Mother, are you writing a letter to Father?
母上 父上に文を
Yes.
ええ
Some things,
あることを
I think, are better explained clearly
あなたの父上には
to your father.
はっきり伝えておきたいの
There is a problem with Cui Jun's identity.
崔浚の素性には問題がある
So is with the wrongful convictions of the An and Lu families
かつての安陸の二氏の冤罪も
years ago, I'm afraid.
恐らく何かあるわ
So you're not going back to Jiankang, Mother?
では母上は剣慷へは戻らないのですか
No. What about you?
あなたは
Are you planning
まさか
to go to the Northern Border with Xiao Wuyi?
蕭無衣と共に北境へ行くつもり
Mother, I'm not...
母上 違います
I made a promise to my master.
これは師匠との約束です
I must not break my word.
破るわけにはいきません
Yaoyao,
夭夭
what do you think of Xiao Wuyi?
蕭無衣をどう思う
Did you have a good time living
靖安王府での日々は
in Prince Jing'an's Mansion?
息災に過ごせた
Mother.
母上
I think...
そうですね
he's somewhat different from what people say about him.
噂とは少し違う方のようです
He's actually a great general.
素晴らしい将軍だと思います
"Who says we stand alone?
“衣がないなどと”
We share weal and woe."
“そなたと衣を共にせん”
Indeed, he chose
確かに自分に
a rather good name for himself.
いい名をつけたものね
But I was asking your opinion about him as a person.
でも私が聞きたいのは 彼の人となりです
He...
あの人は
could be quite annoying sometimes.
時に鼻につくところもありますが
But, I guess, maybe he can be
でも 多分
considered a gentleman.
君子なのでしょう
Let bygones be bygones.
過ぎたことは水に流しましょう
Young Lord Xiao has agreed to let you go.
蕭世子様が許してくださったからには
Have you made any plans
今後の身の振り方は
for your future?
考えているの
I'll travel the world with you for sure, Mother.
もちろん 母上と天下を巡るわ
Haven't you already planned it all out?
母上が計画してくれたんでしょう
In the past, I was so immature
昔の私は物分かりが悪くて
that I often made you angry.
いつも母上を困らせてた
From now on, I will stick with you all the time.
これからは毎日 母上にくっついて
We shall never be apart.
ずっと離れないわ
How about that?
ね
You're leaving so soon?
もう行ってしまうのか
What happened at Lingfeng Fort will be known.
凌風堡のことは隠しきれぬ
I'm afraid the Phoenix Heart Tokens
この道中 多くの者が
will be coveted by many along the way.
雀骨令に欲を出すだろう
If I travel with you,
私がそなたらと共に行けば
there might be danger.
危険が及ぶやもしれぬ
So I'll take a different route back to Jiankang.
私は別の道で剣慷へ戻る
Will you...
剣慷へ？
go back to my mansion
戻るの？
in Jiankang?
靖安王府へ
My mother and I will send Lejun back to Jiankang first,
私と母上でまず楽君様を剣慷までお送りし
and then head directly south to Shu County.
そのまま南下して蜀郡へ向かうわ
Shu County?
蜀郡か
Yes. My mother
母上がね
told me she once saw crystal-clear pools there,
あそこで清池に会ったことがあると
so I'd like to go and see for myself.
だから私も行ってみたくて
Then...
なら
Try not to get kidnapped.
誰かにさらわれるなよ
Don't worry.
心配しないで
I'll continue the studies
師匠の火蒺藜は
on my master's caltrop fireball.
私が研究を続けるから
If anything comes up,
何か分かったら
I'll inform you immediately.
すぐに知らせるわ
Good.
ああ
Well then...
じゃあ
I'll get going.
もう行くね
Sure.
ああ
Li!
李さん
Here you come.
へい
The usual, half salty and half sweet?
いつもの 塩味と甘いのを半々で
Yes.
へいへい
Wait a moment.
少々お待ちを
My wife
うちの奥方がね
loves the rice cake you make.
李さんの餌餅が大好物で
After being away for days,
長く家を離れていたから
I bet she misses this delicacy.
この味が恋しいはずなんだ
How very lucky of your wife to have you,
奥方様は旦那様のように想われて
such a caring man, as her husband.
前世で徳を積まれたのでしょうな
Alright. Thanks.
はは ありがとう
Goodbye.
へい
Master.
家主様
A secret letter has arrived.
密書が届きました
I've found out the mysterious Phoenix Heart Token is related to a mine.
雀骨令の謎は鉱床にあり
Besides,
また
Princess Yunzhao and Cui Jun
雲昭郡主と崔浚は
each hold a Phoenix Heart Token.
各々が雀骨令を一枚所持
The relationship between Xie Jiayu
謝嘉魚と蕭無衣は
and Xiao Wuyi has changed.
以前とは違う
Princess Yunzhao will possibly join forces with Xiao Wuyi.
郡主が蕭無衣と手を組む恐れあり
I'm ready to go all out.
一か八か賭けに出る所存
Why would she partner with Xiao Wuyi?
郡主が蕭無衣と手を組むだと
T-That's impossible.
そ…そんなはずはない
Do not act rashly.
軽はずみな行動は慎め
We'll devise a plan when you're back to Jiankang.
剣慷へ戻ってから策を練る
Have this letter delivered to Princess Pingning.
この文を平寧県主に届けさせよ
Remember: make it quick.
よいか 急げ
Yes.
はっ
Your Highness, Lady Xie,
郡主様 謝夫人
Young Lord Xiao ordered Qing Long and me to escort you two.
世子様のご命令で 私と青龍がお二方をお送りします
How thoughtful of him.
世子様のお心遣いに感謝します
Let's go, Mother.
行きましょう 母上
Anything wrong?
どうかしましたか
Mother, I'm feeling a bit unwell.
母上、少し気分が優れません
Yaoyao, after the incident you just went through,
夭夭、大変な目に遭ったばかりだから
I'm sure you need to lie down and rest.
まだ安静にしていたほうがいいでしょう
Why not ride with me instead, Princess Yunzhao?
私と同じ馬車はいかが
It's a good idea.
ええ
I'm fine, Mother.
大丈夫です 母上
I have recovered.
もうすっかりよくなりました
Maybe we should still...
ですから やはりご一緒させてください
Yaoyao,
夭夭
please listen to Princess Yunzhao.
郡主のお言葉に甘えなさい
If you get ill,
お体の具合が悪いと
everyone will be very worried.
皆が心配しますよ
Be a good girl.
いい子ね
Get some rest.
ゆっくりお休みなさい
My Lady,
お嬢様
His Highness said
世子様が
you must not tire yourself out.
無理をなさらぬようにと
Who on earth do you work for, me or him?
一体 どっちの味方なの
As long as it's for Your Ladyship's own good,
お嬢様のためになることでしたら
I'll listen to it.
誰の言うことでも聞きますわ
I don't think Your Ladyship is rushing to draft the caltrop fireball
お嬢様が火蒺藜の絵を急いでいるのは
entirely for Master Yuan.
元師匠のためだけではない気がします
The horse got startled!
馬が暴走を
Oh no!
まずい
Mother, Lejun!
母上 楽君
Mother!
母上
Xiao Wuyi, let go of me!
蕭無衣 放して
Let go of me!
放して
Mother...
母上
Your Highness!
郡主
-Princess Pingning! -Princess Yunzhao!
県主 郡主
-Mother!
郡主 母上
Princess Pingning!
県主
Princess Yunzhao!
郡主
-Princess Yunzhao! -Princess Pingning!
郡主 県主 県主
Mother...
母上
Princess Pingning!
県主
-Princess Pingning! -Princess Yunzhao!
県主 郡主
Princess Yunzhao!
郡主 郡主
-Mother! -Princess Pingning!
母上 県主
Princess Yunzhao!
郡主
Mother...
母上
Princess Pingning!
県主
-Princess Yunzhao! -Mother...
郡主 母上
-Princess Pingning! -Mother!
県主 母上
Princess Yunzhao!
郡主
I found Her Highness!
見つけました
Mother...
母上
The daughter I want
私が望む娘は
is not some puppet who only knows how to obey me,
私の言いなりの人形ではないの
but a young woman
そうではなく
who truly knows what she wants
本当に望むものを知り
and what she ought to do.
すべきことを分かっている娘よ
Your parents are not the ones you can truly depend on—
頼れるのは親ではなく
only you are.
あなた自身なの
Mother!
母上
Your Highness, the coachman is dead.
世子様 御者は死んでおりました
What about Princess Pingning?
平寧県主は
Not found yet.
まだ見つかっておりません
Go on with the search.
捜索を続けろ
Make sure you find her,
生きていれば本人を
dead or alive.
死んでいれば亡骸を
Yes.
はっ
Mother...
母上
My Lady.
お嬢様
these are Her Highness's belongings.
これは郡主様の遺品です
Is anything missing?
何か足りないものでも
The Phoenix Heart Token...
雀骨令が
Could it have dropped somewhere when Her Highness
郡主様が落ちた時に
fell off the cliff?
落としたのでは
That's impossible.
あり得ません
I saw Mother place it right next to her skin.
母上が肌身離さずお持ちだったのをこの目で見ました
Is Your Ladyship suspecting that someone murdered Her Highness
お嬢様は 誰かが令を奪うため
in order to obtain the token?
郡主様の命を狙ったと
Before she fell off the cliff,
崖から落ちる前
that horse was clearly out of control.
あの馬は明らかに暴れていました
Mother!
母上
Go examine the forage
兵糧を調べて
and the dead coachman.
それと死んだ馬丁も
Got it.
はい
We found Princess Pingning!
県主様が見つかりました
We found Her Highness!
見つかりました
Where did you find her?
どこで
Your Highness was fortunately
県主様は幸運にも
caught on a dead branch right by the cliff.
崖っぷちの枯れ枝に引っかかっておられました
Injured though,
負傷なされましたが
Her Highness's life is not in danger.
命に別状はございません
That's good.
それならよかった
I investigated many a matter.
南星が調べたところ
This is roughly how the incident happened.
大まかな状況は以上です
The horse went wild
馬が暴れたのは
because it ate the grains and forage
汚水に汚染された
contaminated by the dirty water.
稲の兵糧を食べたからです
And all those grains and forage
その稲の兵糧は
were already sealed by my order.
私の命令ですべて差し押さえさせました
I even specifically prepared a horse carriage.
わざわざ馬車まで用意した
Now the biggest suspect of Princess Yunzhao's murder
今や郡主様殺害の第一容疑者は
is me.
この私だ
It does appear so.
表向きはそうです
But Lady Xie is very perceptive.
ですが謝夫人は聡明な方
The clearer the evidence against Your Highness,
証拠が明らかであればあるほど
the less likely Her Ladyship is to suspect you.
世子様を疑いはしないでしょう
Whether she suspects me or not doesn't matter.
私が疑われようと重要ではありません
The point is, the deceased is Jiayu's mother.
ですが あの方は嘉魚の母上です
Now, the more care I show,
今は
the messier the situation will be.
愛情が判断を狂わせる
My Lady!
お嬢様
Are you alright, My Lady?
どうされました お嬢様
Jiayu.
嘉魚
She's burning up.
こんなに熱い
Quick, go get Ruisheng!
早く 蕊生を呼んで
Xiao Wuyi.
蕭無衣
Before my mother's fall,
母上が事故に遭う前
had you seen her
会わなかったか
or heard her mention
あるいは誰かの名を口にしたり
anyone trying to harm her?
自分を害そうとする者がいると
Does sitting in that chair
あの椅子に座れば
mean all the constraints will go away?
誰にも縛られずに済むと
The military is controlled by noble families.
名家が兵を握っている
Whoever takes that post is bound to be
誰があの座に就こうと
subject to constraints.
必ず縛られる
That's why I established Beifu,
だからこそ北府を築き
an army that doesn't answer to noble families.
名家に属さぬ軍を立ち上げたのだ
No.
ない
Father...
父上
Mother...
母上
♪ One glance from near stirs my heart ♪
蕭無衣
I'm here.
ここにいる
Xie Jiayu,
謝嘉魚
do you know who you are asking for?
誰を呼んでいるか分かっているのか
Jiayu
嘉魚
Don't be afraid.
怖がるな
Get some sleep.
眠れ
Dawn will eventually arrive.
必ず夜は明ける
Not all the toxins from the polluted water were cleared from Jiayu's system.
嘉魚殿の体内の毒はまだ抜けきっておらず
Neither did she have time to rest properly.
ろくに休養も取れないうちに
Then, Princess Yunzhao's death hit her hard.
郡主様の件で心労がたたり
She turned like this due to emotional blows.
急に悪化したのです
The remaining toxins in her must be purged.
残った毒を取り除くには
What medicinal materials are needed?
必要な薬材は
I'll have Qing Long go buy them.
青龍に買わせる
I have all the common kinds,
普通のものは揃っていますが
but a rare one is lacking—
希少なものが一つ足りません
bear gall.
熊胆です
My Lady, you're awake.
お嬢様 お目覚めですか
How long was I asleep?
私はどれくらい眠っていたの
Two days.
二日になります
What is this?
これは何
It smells terrible.
なんて生臭くて臭いの
It's bear gall, a cure for toxins.
解毒のための熊の胆です
Where did it come from?
熊の胆なんてどこから
Probably provided by Madam Ruisheng.
おそらく蕊夫人様のものでしょう
That treasure box of hers surely has
あの方の宝箱には
all sorts of medicinal materials, right?
どんな薬でも入っていますから
The journey has been paused for too long.
長居をしすぎたわ
It's time we headed back to Jiankang.
剣慷に戻らないと
My Lady,
お嬢様
Princess Yunzhao passed away so suddenly.
郡主様はあまりに突然お亡くなりに
How should we hold a funeral for Her Highness?
ご葬儀はいかがいたしましょう
Theorectically,
筋から言えば
since Her Highness already divorced the Grand Tutor,
太傅様と郡主様はすでに離縁なされています
her coffin should be placed in the Princess's Mansion.
郡主様は郡主府に安置されるべきかと
However, the princess's fief,
しかし郡主様の封土である
namely Yun County, was conquered by Northern Qin long ago.
雲郡はとうに北秦の手に落ち
Her control over it was just nominal.
食邑は名ばかりです
Neither was her mansion
剣慷にも雲昭郡主府は
ever relocated to Jiankang.
再建されておりません
Then where should we bring her coffin?
ではどちらにご遺体を安置すれば
To Prince Jing'an's Mansion?
靖安王府ですか
From now on, I'll stick with you all the time.
これからは夭夭が毎日そばにいてあげる
We shall never be apart.
ずっと離れないわ
Your Highness!
世子様
Prince Qi and the Grand Tutor have come.
岐王様と太傅様です
Yaoyao, where is Lejun?
夭夭 楽君は
In the carriage behind.
楽君は後ろの馬車に
She fell off the cliff with my mother,
母上と共に崖から落ち
and is still in a coma with severe injuries.
今も重傷で意識がありません
Bring her back to the palace now,
急ぎ宮殿へ
and summon royal physicians!
侍医を呼べ
How did Princess Pingning
なぜ平寧県主が
and Yunzhao fall off the cliff together?
雲昭と共に崖から落ちたのです
Father,
父上
it was all my fault.
私のせいです
I was supposed to share a carriage with Lejun,
元は私と楽君が同乗するはずでした
but I felt unwell
しかし私が体調を崩し
and needed to lie down,
横になる必要があったため
so we swapped carriages.
馬車を替わったのです
Because the horse was startled,
馬が驚いたせいで
her carriage plunged off the cliff.
馬車ごと崖から落ちてしまいました
Father,
父上
I...
私は
Grand Tutor,
太傅様
Jiayu didn't wish for
郡主様の死は
Princess Yunzhao's death,
嘉魚が望んだことではなく
nor does she have anything to do with it.
彼女とは無関係です
How does it have nothing to do with her?
どうして無関係だと言える
Who told you to switch carriages with Yunzhao?
誰が雲昭と馬車を替えろと言った
If it had never happened,
もし替わっていなければ
it would've been you who died.
死んでいたのはお前だ
It couldn't have been Yunzhao, right?
なぜ雲昭なんだ
Everyone of the Xie family, listen!
謝氏一同 聞くがよい
Princess Yunzhao and I simply adopted Xie Jiayu.
謝嘉魚はただの養女であり
She was not given birth by us.
私と郡主の実の娘ではない
From now on,
これより
this woman is no longer the daughter of the Xie family.
謝氏はこの娘を認めぬ
She is not allowed
この娘が二度と謝府に
to step into the Xie Mansion ever again.
足を踏み入れることを許さぬ
Guards!
者共
Yes.
はっ
Escort the princess's coffin
郡主様の棺を
back home.
屋敷へお連れしろ
Yes.
はっ
On the genealogical record,
一族の系図において
I, Xie Huaigui, and Yunzhao,
雲昭は生涯
will remain as husband and wife forever.
この謝懐帰の妻である
We were never divorced.
離縁などしておらぬ
I'm taking my wife home.
妻を屋敷へ連れて帰る
None of you can stop me.
止められるものなら止めてみよ
Grand Tutor!
太傅様
Xiao Wuyi, go back without me.
蕭無衣 先に帰っていてくれ
I need a word
少し話がある
with Mao.
阿茂さんに話さないと
I didn't expect you to be involved in the Cui Family Case.
まさか崔氏の事件に巻き込まれるなんて
I was frightened upon receiving
楽君から手紙が来た時は
that letter from Lejun.
心底驚いたわ
Don't beat yourself up.
自分を責めないで
What happened to Lejun and Princess Yunzhao was an accident.
楽君と郡主様のことは事故だった
It wasn't your fault.
あなたのせいじゃない
My mother didn't die of an accident.
母上は事故で死んだんじゃない
What?
何ですって
Her Phoenix Heart Token has gone missing.
母上の雀骨令が消えたの
Someone must have
何者かが
murdered her for the token,
雀骨令を奪うために母上を手にかけ
and Lejun became collateral damage.
楽君まで巻き込んだのよ
Do the Phoenix Heart Tokens truly exist?
本当に雀骨令が
Cui Jun and my mother each had one.
崔浚と母上が１つずつ持っていた
If it hadn't been for these tokens,
あの令のせいで
I wouldn't have been tricked into going to Lingfeng Fort by Cui Jun.
私は崔浚にだまされ凌風堡へ
He originally intended to use me
崔浚は私を人質に
to force my mother to hand over her token.
母上から雀骨令を奪うつもりだったけど
Yet he failed in the end.
失敗に終わった
I find Xiao Wuyi suspicious.
蕭無衣が怪しいわ
The horse went wild
馬が狂ったのは
for eating the grains in Lingfeng Fort,
凌風堡の
which were polluted by the dirty mine water.
鉱水に汚染された稲を食べたせい
All those grains
その稲は
had been collected and sealed by Xiao Wuyi.
蕭無衣が押収し封鎖した
No one could access them except him.
彼以外に持っている者はいない
He already coveted the Cui family's mines
彼は凌風堡にいた頃から
back in Lingfeng Fort.
崔氏の鉱山を狙っていた
So he's the biggest suspect.
だから最も疑わしい
Lejun is severely injured and in a coma now.
楽君は重傷でまだ目覚めない
When she comes to, please
もし目覚めたら
ask her to do me a favor and think carefully
人証などの手がかりを
if there is any other witness or clue.
思い出せないか 聞いてみて
I've someone to find the coachman's family
御者の家族を探させているの
in the hope of gaining new clues.
何か手がかりがあればと
But, Yaoyao,
でも夭夭さん
if you're truly suspecting Wuyi,
本気で無衣を疑うなら
then you must not return to his mansion.
靖安王府には戻れないわよ
If not, how am I supposed to find
靖安王府に戻らなければ
my mother's Phoenix Heart Token?
どうやって雀骨令を探すの
This item is of great importance.
あの令はとても重要よ
He must have hidden it somewhere secret.
きっと人目に付かない場所に隠してる
Perhaps he has it on him.
あるいは懐に
As long as I find this token,
雀骨令さえ見つければ
I'll be able to prove him to be the murderer.
彼が犯人だと証明できるわ
Yaoyao...
夭夭さん
Mao.
阿茂さん
My mother is dead.
母上が亡くなったの
The only person who loved me unconditionally
この世で唯一 私だけを愛してくれた人が
in this world died a wrongful death.
こんなふうに理不尽に死んだなんて
I swear to find out the murderer,
必ず母上を殺した犯人を見つけ出す
whoever that may be.
相手が誰であろうと
I will make sure justice is served for her.
必ず母上の無念を晴らすわ
Maybe Your Highness
世子
should have the bear-induced wounds checked by the physicians.
熊の爪による傷は侍医にお見せください
Have Cui Jun and Cui Shao'an
崔浚と崔少安の件は
been properly arranged?
どうなった
Yes, all is done as per Your Highness's orders.
仰せのとおりに手配済みです
What happened at Lingfeng Fort will soon be known.
凌風堡の件は隠し通せません
With two Phoenix Heart Tokens appearing at once,
２つの雀骨令が現れたとあっては
anyone would be tempted.
誰もが色めき立ちます
I'd like to see
誰が食らいついてくるか
who will show up for them.
見ものだな
Xiao Wuyi, I'm back.
蕭無衣 戻ったわ
You finished that talk with Yizhi?
易之とは話し終えたか
Yes, I was giving him some advice about Lejun.
楽君のことで頼みごとを
Are you explaining to me?
私に弁解か
I'd like to have a clean room.
清潔な部屋が欲しいの
Wensheng Courtyard has always been yours.
聞笙苑はずっとお前のものだ
I want to set up a memorial tablet.
位牌を置きたいの
Before my mother died,
母上は生前
she had decided to divorce that man.
あの人との離縁を決めていた
I'm afraid her spirit in heaven
母上の魂は
would hate to return to the Grand Tutor's Mansion.
太傅府には戻りたくないはず
So, I plan to set up a memorial tablet
だから聞笙苑に
for her in Wensheng Yard.
位牌を置いて
This way, I can mourn for her.
喪に服したいの
As I said,
言ったはずだ
Wensheng Yard has always been yours.
聞笙苑はずっとお前のものだ
Feel free to make your own decision.
自分で決めればいい
Got it.
分かった
Lejun,
楽君
the imperial physician said
侍医の話では
you hit your head when you fell off the cliff.
崖から落ちた時 頭を打ったそうだ
That's why you've been in a coma.
だから眠り続けていると
Are you going to stay asleep like this
まさかこのまま
and never wake up again?
二度と目を覚まさないつもりか
What exactly happened
あの馬車で
in the carriage?
何があったんだ
Yaoyao said
夭夭の話では
Xiao Wuyi murdered Princess Yunzhao to get her Phoenix Heart Token.
蕭無衣が雀骨令を奪うため郡主を手にかけたと
She has also sent people
夭夭は人を遣わし
to find the coachman's family.
御者の家族を見つけ出した
Though the latter is dead,
御者は死んだが
his family might have seen
その家族が
who replaced the forage
兵糧を稲にすり替えるのを
with the polluted grains.
目撃した可能性がある
As long as the witnesses arrive in Jiankang,
証人が剣慷に戻りさえすれば
they can immediately testify
すぐに証言できる
who exactly harmed you and Princess Yunzhao.
お前と郡主を害した犯人を
Li Lejun, you're actually conscious, aren't you?
李楽君 目が覚めているんだろう
Are you sure you want to keep up the act?
まだ芝居を続ける気か
Mao.
兄上
Are you alright?
ご無事ですか
Have Yaoyao and her people really found
夭夭たちは本当に見つけたのですか
the coachman's family?
御者の家族を
Did they truly see who tempered with the forage?
本当に目撃したと
No...
まさか
It can't be possible.
あり得ない
So it really was you.
やはりお前だったか
Please punish me, Mao.
兄上 どうか罰を
Why on earth did you do it?
なぜだ
This matter has nothing to do with you.
これは兄上には関わりませぬ
It's better for you not to know the truth.
お知りにならぬほうが
You caused Princess Yunzhao's death,
郡主を手にかけ
and framed Xiao Wuyi for it.
蕭無衣にぬれぎぬを着せたな
Xiao Wuyi is not someone to be trifled with.
蕭無衣は甘い相手ではないぞ
Tell the truth already.
今 話さねば
If not, what are you going to do
奴が調べ始めた時
when he starts investigating it?
どうするつもりだ
Speak up.
言え
Prior your trip to Guazhou,
鴰州へ行く前に
what exactly did you plot with the Grand Tutor?
太傅と何をたくらんだ
Why did you murder Princess Yunzhao?
なぜ郡主を手にかけた
Because she had a Phoenix Heart Token.
郡主が雀骨令を持っていたからです
Because Crown Prince Wenxi is still alive.
文熹太子がご存命だからです
And more importantly,
そして何より
Princess Yunzhao knew that you, my brother, are
郡主は兄上が
the Grand Tutor's son.
太傅の息子だと知っていたからです
What?
何だと